welcome back to AP US History in under 3
minutes no time for intros let's get
into it topic 1.4 is all about the
Colombian Exchange and how it impacted
Europe and the Americas so first we need
to define the Colombian Exchange by
definition the Colombian Exchange means
the transfer of goods Foods animals
flora fauna diseases and slaves between
the Americas and Europe after European
contact in the Americas essentially what
happened is when European countries came
to America various things got
transferred from one continent to the
other the Americas had revolutionary
crops like maze potatoes tomatoes and
tobacco that got transferred to Europe
the influx of these foods to Europe
caused there to be a population boom and
the transfer of goods allowed for Europe
to shift from an economic system of
feudalism where land was owned by Nobles
and worked by peasants to capitalism
where trade and Industry are controlled
by private owners for profit also during
this time Maritime Technologies
underwent massive improvements such as
the caravel and astr meaning it was
easier for people to explore what also
made it easier was the implementation of
joint stock companies this was a company
that a bunch of people could pull their
money into so if it did well they would
all earn money if not they could only
lose their initial investment so it was
very low risk these joint stock
companies were the companies funding
these voyages to the Americas as for
Europe's effect on the Americas yes
there was Goods foods and animals
brought to the Americas like wheat rice
horses and pigs but the the biggest
thing that came from Europe to the
Americas was deadly diseases Europeans
had been living with diseases like small
poox and measles for many centuries and
had gained a sort of natural immunity to
them the natives however did not have
the same immunity and therefore when
these diseases got introduced it said
that 50 to 90% of the native population
died because of them and that's all for
this video on the screen now are some AP
style questions for this video pause
now I'll put the answers on the screen
now see in the next one